Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 4 -- Letters to Franklin 1779 January-November Mss.B.F85inventory04
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Congratulating him on his appointment as Minister Plenipotentiary. The sincerity of their devotion to America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    Has received a letter from John Lotcher, master of the "Victoria," one of two Swedish ships sent to France to be examined; he reports his arrival at Bas Island and his having lost sight of the other ship, "Anna Louisa," in a fog.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 18; L.S. 3p.; Lavabre, Doerner and Co. Paris
    Asking for the return of a certain sum of money placed with Franklin's bankers to the account of M. [Pierre] Colomb, who, however, never touched it. Desires to know if vessels sailing under the Genoese flag can trade freely with the United States.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Lafreté, Jean-Jacques de. Paris
    Asking for the promised letter of recommendation; sends a packet for M. Gérard which he begs Franklin to forward.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roux, C.J. Paris
    Asking that M. Marin be informed of the day and hour when he (Le Roux) will read about a new, patriotic and disinterested institution.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, Arthur, Chailot
    Expects to call the next day and congratulate him on his appointment. Desires nothing more earnestly than to cultivate the harmony recommended in the Resolution of Congress; therefore, he will not, as he had intended, demand an explanation of Franklin's apparent concurrence with Mr. Deane in his outrageous abuse of himself.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 18; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Recommending M. Panier as one of the ablest manufacturers of printing presses; his desire to set up his business in America. Hopes to have a talk with him at M. de la Blancherie's Assembly, which meets that day; congratulates him on his appointment as Minister Plenipotentiary.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Will remain in London until the arrival of Mr. Hartley, to whom he will deliver Franklin's letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Walkar, John. Paimboeuf
    After serving three years in the service of the United States, was taken prisoner by the English and brought to England; made his escape and went to Dunkirk where he was refused aid by Mr. Coffyn; started for Paris, but his money giving out and being unable to speak French, he was enlisted in the "regiment de Berwick"; desires to be sent back to Pennsylvania.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Bret, Antoine. Paris
    Having heard that Franklin is commissioned to have a gold sword made for the Marquis de la Fayette, recommends one of his friends who is willing to part with a magnificent sword, made for the late King of Portugal.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 19; A.L.S. 1p.; G.B. Gillon, Susanna Hodenpyl. Bath
    Enclosing a letter for her brother, Mr. Alexander Gillon, of Charleston, who expects to be in Paris in a few days.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Vicq d' Azyr, Félix
    Inviting Franklin to be present at a meeting of the Royal Society of Medicine.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 February 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Rectification of the mistake relative to Mr. Simcon Deane's goods.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 February 20; 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished to the States of Maryland, New York, Massachusetts-Bay and Delaware.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 20; A.L.S. 1p. ;1p.; Saint-Pierre Dutalli (Dutaillis), Joseph-Nicolas. The Frigate Concord
    Officer and engineer in the American service; sends a copy of a letter written to M. de Sartine; his unfortunate experience and present imprisonment on board the frigate "Concord."
    [Notes in English on back of Mss.] In M. de St. Pierre's letter to M. de Sartine, he confessed that, knowing how inhumanly the French prisoners were treated, he wrote a letter to the Governor of Jamaica proposing a plan for conquering Carolina and Georgia; encloses this plan and points out its palpable absurdity and the object for which it was written. His imprisonment at St. Domingo; later, sent a prisoner to France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 20; L in 3d P. 1p.; Desgranges and Co. Paris
    Sending a prospectus of their armament, and asking that Franklin and his friends should aid an enterprise, whose object is to insure commercial prosperity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Durif de Cazaneuve, Capt. La Rochelle
    Commanded "Le Marquis de la Fayette," in the service of Messrs. Mease, Barclay, Caldwell and Co., of Philadelphia; taken prisoner by the English and detained three months at Halifax; exchanged by the Comte d'Estaing and arrived finally at La Rochelle; need of money; begs Franklin to accept a letter of exchange which was drawn on Messrs. Gruel, of Nantes, who refused to pay it.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 February 20; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Asking for a letter of marque for the ship, "Mary Fearon." Concerning a letter from the President of the Navy Board at Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Brutière, G. Anquetil. Granville
    Reminding Franklin of his promise to redress his (Brutiere's) wrongs; was compelled by an American privateer to take on board his ship seven English prisoners, who consumed the major part of his supplies, and forced him to return to Dieppe; desires indemnification for his losses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 21; A.L.S. 4p.; Hamelin, -----. Nantes
    [Joseph] Belton, an American, after boarding with him six months, left without paying; he promised to send the money upon his arrival in Paris whither he went to show Franklin a new kind of gun; begs Franklin's interest to obtain it for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Lee, Arthur. Chaillot
    Acknowledging Franklin's letter of the 18th inst. in which he desires all the papers belonging to their department; reason why he declines to give up the few original papers in his possession relating to the transactions of their late joint Commission; if Congress orders it, will cede the point.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 22; A.L.S. 4p.; Mante, Thomas. Fort l'Eveque
    Obliged to have recourse to Franklin's bounty once again; the obduracy of his antagonist, which all the efforts of M. Turgot cannot soften, still subjects him to an unjust imprisonment; for want of a small sum of money, is unable to record his letters of naturalization. Has translated M. Dupont's Table of the Principles of Political Economy into English; desires to dedicate it to Franklin. His hope of retruning one day to America.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 February 22; A.L.S. 2p.; Taverne Demont Dhiver. Dunkirk
    Influenced by their recommendation, given to Captains Marchant and Arnold, both of Boston, is ready to employ them on his vessel, the "Comte de Maurepas"; desires Franklin to send two commissions to them, under his care.
  - to W.T. Franklin, 1779 February 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Desiring that the enclosed pamphlet and letter may be forwarded to Mr. Silas Deane. Refers him to a certain page and line of his latest work for the quatrain referring to Franklin.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1779 February 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Report just received from La Rochelle of the arrival there of a State vessel loaded with tobacco; no particulars as yet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Answers to certain questions about Mr. Mercier.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Answer to the French Ambassador returned as not satisfactory.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    Congratulating him on his appointment as Minister Plenipotentiary, Begs him to interfere in the matter of exorbitant duties levied on some old furniture of his.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Gridley, Joseph. Nantes
    Desiring the position of Consul to the United States in France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Thompson, Benjamin. Nantes
    Is a native of Boston and a son of the late Captain Thompson who commanded the galley, " Experiment," in the service of Pennsylvania; gave up his commission in the army to take up commerce; his unsuccessful expedition to France; his present situation without money or friends; desires Franklin to procure him some honest employment and to help him out of his most pressing difficulties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 25; L.S. 2p.; Dubois, Henrÿ. Amsterdam
    Desires Franklin to send the enclosed letter to Messrs. Wallisch and Hancock, as he is furnishing them with various article in his trade. Reports that the ship commanded by Captain Moses Grinnell, from Boston, and destined for Amsterdam, has arrived at Rotterdam.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Le Roux, C.J. Paris
    Begging Franklin to deliver to M. Necker the memoir, entitled, "Plan d'un nouvel Etablissement patriotique et désinteressé"; if this plan merits Franklin's approbation, has another copy for him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; L.S. 3p.; McLaughlin, ----- and Creery, -----. Paimboeuf
    Account of their services in the army of the United States and their arrival in France in the "Boston" firgate commanded by Captain Tucker; were enticed into Berwick's French regiment, and having deserted in order to return to America, were retaken, punished and imprisoned; asks to be redeemed and sent back to the Continental troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    Objects to completing his crew with French sailors. Repairs needed on the "Alliance"; enumerates the advantages of having her sheathed with copper; being thus equipped, sincerely believes there will be no frigate her equal in the world.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; A.L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    Before he set out for Marseilles, to take command of the "Flamand," he spoke to Mr. Deane concerning his compensation and Franklin approved of his views. Action of the Congress in relation thereto. Mr. Deane has been sitting in the Congress a long time, but nothing definite has yet been done. His monthly pay has been due since July 4th, last; has sold all his clothes and spent his cash, and has but nine guineas left.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Information about a certain clique of foreigners in France, enemies to America, who are kept informed by her false friends of all her adherents attempt to do.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; A.N. 1p.; Beaumont, Anne-Louise and Jean-Baptiste-Jacques Elie de. Paris
    Invitation to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 27; L.S. 2p.; Paulze, Jacques. Paris
    Thanking Franklin for the information of the arrival, at L'Orient, of the French ship " La Bergère," loaded with tobacco from Maryland; has written concerning their portion of the cargo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Bordot, François. La Rochelle
    Reporting the appearance, off the coast, of the French frigate, "Courageuse," with an English six and twenty gun privateer in tow: the fight said to have been desperate; no particulars as yet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Marchant, Capt. Stephen
    Has been promised the command of a privateer at Dunkirk; writes to ask for an American commission.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 27; A.L.S. 3p.; MacCreery, William. Bordeaux
    Asking Franklin to procure American merchants the liberty of loading salt at Bordeaux, free of duty; complains that their ships are treated as stangers and obliged to pay duties accordingly.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 28; L.S. 1p.; Conti, Louis-François-Joseph de Bourbon, comte de la Marche and prince de. Paris
    Has arranged with Messrs. de Vergennes and sartine to give him the necessary passports for his stud-groom Riotto [Augustin Badran]; begs also for Franklin's passport; he goes to England to procure dogs and horses.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 28; A.L.S. 2p.; Rousseaux, Jean. Dunkirk
    Claims his salary as well as his prize money due him during the service to Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 26; A.L.S. 1p.; de la Colombes, ------. Au Puy
    Requesting Dr. Franklin to forward in his mail a letter to M. [Conrad Alexandre] Gérard [de Rayneval] which he sends.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    Concerning the trial of the conspirators; urges again the advisability of sheating his vessel with copper; has not time to make an estimate of the expense of all the repairs needed; his reasons for objecting to exchange most of the conspirators and carry three or four of the wickedest to America for trail, as Franklin suggests.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February?; A.L.S. 2p.; Bernardi, Gioanni de
    Desires to settle in America and asks his advice.
    (In Itailan.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 February; A.L.S. 1p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    His Majesty's orders to remain in Paris without seeing a great number of acquaintances; thousand absurd rumors circulated about American affairs; happy to receive Franklin at his house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 1.; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Address presented to the States General and the Holland Assembly by a deputation of Rotterdam merchants, protesting against the wrong done them by the decree published in France; committee appointed to consult thereon with the Admiralty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 2.; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Business connected with his agency at Nantes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 2.; A.L.S. 2p.; Lloyd, Richard Bennett. London
    Sends a copy of a letter received by Mr. Hartley from the Office for Sick and Wounded Seamen; Mr. Hartley's kind reception of him and his promise to send Franklin the earliest intelligence concerning an exchange of prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 2.; A.L.S. 2p.; Hartley, David. London
    Has shared Franklin's discontent respecting the delay in the exchange of prisoners. Has received positive assurance that the first cartel-ship has left Spithead, on her passage to Plymouth, to take on board the first hundred. Has spoken to the Minister concerning Franklin's proposal to send Dr. Bancroft to expedite the exchange, but he thought it needless in so plain a business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 3.; A.L.S. 1p.; Blodget, Nathan. Brest
    Desiring permission to leave the "Alliance," where he holds the position of purser, and go to Paris on his own business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 3.; A.L.S. 2p.; Duverger, -----. Liège
    Offering his service to supply Franklin with arms for the United States.
    A.E. by Franklin. Obliged to the gentleman but has not at present anyorders of that kind to be executed.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 3.; A.L.S. 2p.; Landais, Capt. Pierre. Brest
    In reference to orders from the Navy Board of Boston, as to pay of the ship's company; encloses a copy. Expresses pleasure at the prospect of having the Honorable Mr. Adams as a passenger.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779 ?] March 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Tascher, President
    Recommending the son of the French Consul at Rome for a consulship in that city.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 3; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Decision of the Admiralty already taken; understands that it is to be in accord with Amsterdam's wishes.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1779 March 3; L. 3p.; Bingham, William. St Pierre, Martinique
    Obliged to draw on them to pay for the fitting out of the frigate, "Deane," and the armed brigantine, the "General Gates," now at St. Pierre; justifies this step; Congress indebted to him for a large sum; it is with the greatest difficulty he can support the weight of such heavy advances.
    (Copy in duplicate.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Montaudoüin de la Touche, Jean-Gabriel. Nantes
    Congratulating Franklin on his late appointment. Trusts that he has ceased to be troubled by the gout. Sorry to hear of the lack of success Comte d'Estaing has had. Introducing M. David de Morlaix.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Ridley, Matthew. Nantes
    Congratulating Franklin on his appointment.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Oliver, Richard. London
    Expects to leave shortly for the West Indies with two or three friends; desires Franklin to lend them the protection of his name, should the fate of war make them prisoners.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 4; A.L.S. 4p.; Paine, Thomas. Philadelphia
    Concerning Mr. Deane's inflammatory address, published in the newspapers of December 5th; the influence it exerted on the public; his reply to it; the abuse he met with not only from the people but from Congress. Justifies his attack on Mr. Deane from the papers in his possession; the pains he took not to involve Franklin in this affair; has had an exceeding rough time of it, but the tide of public sentiment has turned in his favor. Sent in his resignation of Secretary to the Committee of Foreign affairs.
    General note
    [Note on MS. by unknown hand. An unfair letter! Paine dismissed from his office as Secretary for using his position to publish the substance of secret despatches.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Mons, Samuel Stanley, baron and -----, baroness de. Altona
    Asking Franklin's influence with Congress that she may obtain possession of her property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Bon de Corcelles, Pierre. Moudon
    His admiration for America; desires to settle there, preferably in Pennsylvania, with several farmers who will go over under his direction; wishes information as to the price of land or whether it is granted gratis.
    A. Dr. of answer by Benjamin Franklin. That the lands in Pennsylvania not yet granted all belong to the Proprietary, Mr. Penn. That he sells them for £5, sterling, the 100 acres. A price so low that probably the gentlemen would chuse rather to purchase than to accept them as a gift. That no lands are given to encourage strangers to settle in that province. A good climate, good air, good soil, good government, good laws and liberty have been sufficient encouragements without hiring inhabitants by other gifts; and all these he will meet with, besides an honest, virtuous people, who receive strangers with a sincere welcome and will respect his talents.
  - to The American Commissioners, 1779 March 5; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Hopkinson. 1p.; The Treasurer of Loans. Philadelphia
    Notification of bills of exchange furnished the States of New Hampshire, New Jersey and Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Baldwin, Charles. London
    Their ardent desire to see him again; his Mrs. Baldwin's regular Sunday entertainment. Hopes his son has received the letters of recommendation sent by Franklin. The profile he alluded to is 2 1/2 inches long, of the Royal Manufactory of Sauve; Miss Watkins promises to kiss it the moment it comes to hand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Requesting instructions regarding the cargo of tobacco arrived from Virginia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Aubry, -----. Luxeuil
    Desires Franklin to procure his son employment in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartmann, Rudolphe Ernest. Amsterdam
    Wrote him the year before, in June, with a request to forward to General Washington his letter concerning the whereabouts of Baron de Zedwitz, who owes him a large sum of money; desires to know if Franklin has received any information.
    A. E. by Franklin. Sent his letter to America, but has heard nothing since.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6; A.L.S. 2p.; MacCreery, William. Bordeaux
    Wrote Franklin concerning the port duties charged on sundry articles shipped by the subjects of the United States. Asks him to obtain permission from the Minister for Messrs. Delap and himself to load the ship "Buckskin" with salt, free of duty. Offers to take any goods bound for Maryland.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6; A.L.S. 1p.; S. and J.H. Delap. Bordeaux
    Asking Franklin to give his decision in the case of a prize brigladen with fish and oil, whose sale was stopped by the Judge of the Admiralty; need of haste owing to the perishable quality of the cargo.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6; A.L.S. 2p.; Johnson, Joshua. Nantes
    Thanking him for his readiness to release him from the duties imposed on his furniture by the Farmers-General; sends a list of the articles involved. Pleased with the appointment of the Alliance to convey their ships to America. Arrival of "La Bergère" with a cargo of tobacco.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6.; A.L.S. 2p.; Roberdeau, Jacques-Dominique. Haguenau
    In February of the proceeding year, sent Franklin a letter to forward to General Daniel Roberdeau, Member of Congress in the United States; having received no answer, encloses another, which he begs may be sent by a safe conveyance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6.; A.L.S. 10p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. L'Orient
    The mystery so delicately mentioned in Franklin's favor of the 24th, he intended to explain much earlier; encloses a copy of the original paper; the subject was communicated to sundry members of Congress at the beginning of the war; after this misfortune of his life, was advised to retire incognito to America until the Admiralty Commission should arrive on the Island; everything changed by the revolution in America; appointments he received in the navy of the Colonies; his summary of his own character. Explains the affair of the pillage of Lord Selkirk's plate;1 his intention to restore it; believes Mr. Alexander to be his enemy; his indifference to spies. Congratulates Franklin on his appointment. Concerning the outfit of the "Poor Richard."
    [Enclosure.] Account of the accidental killing of a mutinous sailor, by the master of West India ship [evidently John Paul Jones himself]; his actions, subsequent to this melancholy accident; reasons why he did not surrender himself for trial.
    Printed in The Independent, April 12, 1906, P. 833.
    1 See also "John Paul Jones Commemoration at Annapolis, April 24, 1906.", Washington, 1907, p. 123 et seq.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1779 March 6.; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    News of the arrival of various ships from America. South Carolina perfectly secure from any attempt of the enemy. The ships at Nantes loaded and ready to sail.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [Circa 1779.] March 6; L. 1p.; -----, -----
    Glad to hear of his welfare; neither of the drafts mentioned have appeared. Wishes they may live to meet when swords and spears are beat into plough shares and pruning hooks.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1779.] March 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Warville, Brissot de